<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A short instruction vnto Christian religion briefly noting our profession, exercise, and obedience required of vs in this life. By Thomas Pearston.</title>
            <author>Pearston, Thomas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1590</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 35 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09211</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19520</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100341</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836184</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836184</idno>
            <idno type="VID">440</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09211)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 440)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1526:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A short instruction vnto Christian religion briefly noting our profession, exercise, and obedience required of vs in this life. By Thomas Pearston.</title>
                  <author>Pearston, Thomas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[30] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by John Wolfe,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1590.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Some print show-through; pages tightly bound and torn.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B[-B8].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Religious education --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:440:1"/> 
               <pb facs="tcp:440:1" rendition="simple:additions"/> A SHORT Inſtruction vnto Chriſtian Religion, <hi>Briefly noting our profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi> exerciſe, and obedience required of vs in this Life.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By Thomas Pearſton.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>1. Peter. 3. 15. &amp; 16.</bibl>
               <p>Sanctify the Lord God in your hartes, and be readie alwaies to giue an anſwere to euery man that asketh you a reaſon of the hope that is in you, with meekenes and reuerence, hauing a good conſcience, that when they ſpeake euil of you as of euil doers, they may be aſhamed which ſlaunder your good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation in Chriſt.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Romaines. 1. 16.</bibl>
               <p>I am not aſhamed of the Goſpell of Chriſt: for it is the power of God vnto ſaluation, to eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one that belieueth.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON Printed by Iohn Wolfe, 1590.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:440:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:440:2"/>
            <head>REVERENDISSIMO IN Chriſto patri Domino Iohanni Londinenſi Epiſcopo vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantiſsimo.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Q</seg>Vm vt inquit Apoſtolus, reuerendiſsime Pater, non ſublimitate ſermonis vel ſapientiae annuntiandum eſt Dei te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonium, nec perſuaſorijs huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae ſapientiae ſermonibus praedican<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum, ſed ſpiritus &amp; potentiae de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtratione: id eſt probatione, quae fit certis &amp; neceſſarijs rationibus, Ieſum Chriſtu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; hunc crucifixum, in infirmitate, in timore, &amp; tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more multo agnoſcere ſimulac pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiteri oportet. Magnopere me haec atque his ſimilia indeſinenter ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo inuoluere conducunt, quonam modo hac noſtra aetate rudiores (qui quidem verba proferre, ſed non intelligere poſſunt) Ieſu Chriſti mortem aliáque quae ad huius vitae <pb facs="tcp:440:3"/> normam, &amp; ad futura<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> immortalita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem magnopere co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ducunt, intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerent. Simplici igitur modo, atta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in Dei timore ad ſimpliciu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formatione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> edificationém<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>palia quidem ac etiam particularia, tum fidei, tu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Decalogi, orationiſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> dominicae parte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brá<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> breuiter componere ſtatui. Veſtro igitur ſtu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dio magná<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> Dei Eccleſiae cura co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnitis ac diuulgatis: ita veheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tius tuae reuerentiae has meas perpauas Queſtionum &amp; Reſpontionu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> anno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tationes dedicare, ſub<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> tui honoris nomine promulgare, me (quaſi cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caribus indigentem) ſtimulauêre. Hanc a tuo Honore meam induſtri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>am quamuis minutiſsima<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, acceptá fore ſperans ad Dei miſericordiam, gratiam, pacém<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> qui omnium eſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Creator, Gubernator, ac conſerua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tor, Honorem tuum precibus mei commendo.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Tui honoris obſeruantiſsimus, Thomas Pearſton.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="catechism">
            <pb facs="tcp:440:3"/>
            <head>¶ <hi>A ſhort inſtruction vnto Chriſtian religion, briefly noting our profeſsion, exerciſe, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience required of vs in this life.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <label>Queſtion.</label> 
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat art thou?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſwere.</label> A creature of God.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> Wherefore did God create and make you?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> To ſerue him.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> When was your name giuen you?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> At my chriſtening.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> By whom was it giuen you?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> By my ſureties which anſwered for me.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> In anſwering for thée, what profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on did they make?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> That I ſhould be brought vp in the feare of God, and ſo ſerue him.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> Why was thy name giuen thée?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Becauſe I ſhould alwaies remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber when I am called by my name, that I was chriſtened to bee Chriſtes
<pb facs="tcp:440:4"/> member, Gods childe, and an heire of heauen:</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> Is it enough to acknowledge this?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> No. except wee endeuour to come thereto.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> Thou ſaideſt that thy ſureties did profeſſe that thou ſhouldeſt be brought vp in the feare of God, and ſerue him: which is the way to ſerue him?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> In obaying his commandements.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> Which is the way to bring vp one in the feare of God?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> To teach them to knowe Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> What is Ieſus Chriſt?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> The end of the law.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> How muſt Ieſus Chriſt be known?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> By faith.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> How can one belieue the Artickles of faith, hath he power of him ſelfe to belieue them, and all things contained in them?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> No verely, for of our ſelues wee can not doe any thing.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> How ſo? whence haue we this faith then?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> From heauen, it is Gods gift, and
<pb facs="tcp:440:4"/> not our diſpoſition.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> Séeing thou ſayeſt this gift of faith doth come from heauen, and that it is Gods. Tell me how we might get vs this faith.</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> By hearing Gods word preached.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> Is it enough to heare Gods worde to be preached, and ſo to goe our way?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> We muſt both heare it and kéepe it.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> How many things doth Gods word teach vs?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Firſt obedience to the law, ſecondly, faith in Chriſt, thirdly, the vſe of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, and fourthly, prayer.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> So then thou doeſt confeſſe, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can be done without prayer?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Truth it is.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> Who commaundeth prayer?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Chriſt him ſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> Is there nothing els required of vs, but onely obedience, faith, the vſe of the Sacraments, and prayer: ought wee not alſo to be thankfull?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> We can not render too high thanks vnto God.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> When we haue giuen thankes, is it enough that God hath put vs in minde <pb facs="tcp:440:5"/> ſo once to doe?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> As we begin ſo ought we to continue in praying for the encreaſe of faith.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> Say the ſumme of faith or créede.</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> I belieue in God the Father almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> What be the chiefeſt pointes of the beliefe?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> The firſt is of God the Father, the ſecond of God the Sonne, the third of God the holy Ghoſt, the fourth and laſt of the Church and benefits therof.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> As we haue the chiefe partes of the beliefe, ſo let vs conſider the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars: and to begin, tell mee what ye learne in the firſt word of the Créede, what is it to belieue in God?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> By this I learne to put my full truſt and confidence in him alone.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> What learne ye in this: maker of heauen?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> That God made mee and all the world.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> Why is God called almightie?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Becauſe he hath all might and power to rule all thinges according to his will.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:440:5"/>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> What learne you in theſe words? And in Ieſus Chriſt his onely Sonne?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> I learne that Chriſt is the onely na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall ſonne of God.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> Why call you him Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Becauſe he is my redéemer and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> Why doe you ſay our Lord and not my Lord?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> For that he is not onely my Lord, but alſo the ſauiour of all the faithfull.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> Thou ſaieſt in the beliefe, that Chriſt was borne: by whom was he borne?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Of Mary a pure and perfect uirgin.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> How was Mary Chriſtes mother, in that he is God, or in that he is man?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> In that he is man.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> How is he the onely ſonne of God, in that he is man, or in that he is God?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> In that he is God from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> Séeing Chriſt is the ſecond perſon in Trinitie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and equall to the Father in the Godhead: why did he humble him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſo low to take on him mans nature in the wombe of the Virgin?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> For this cauſe, that ſinne which raig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <pb facs="tcp:440:6"/> in our fleſh, might be puniſhed in his fleſh.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> How was Chriſt conceiued in her wombe.</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> By the power of the holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> What was Pilate?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> The ruler of the Iewes.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> Why did Chriſt ſuffer vnder an earth<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly Iudge or ruler?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> To declare his innocency.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> What profite haue wee by Chriſtes innocencie and righteouſneſſe?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> We are made righteous by it in the ſight of God.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> Why was he crucifyed?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> For our ſinnes.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> Why did Chriſt die?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> To deliuer the faithfull from eternall death.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> Why was he buried?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> For an aſſurance of his death.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> VVho buried him?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Ioſeph and Nicodemus.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> There were many called Ioſeph, as Ioſeph foſter father to Chriſt, and Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph which dwelled at a place called A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramathea, and diuers others, which <pb facs="tcp:440:6"/> of theſe was he that did helpe to burie Chriſt?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Ioſeph which dwelled at Aramathea.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> VVhat meaneth Chriſts deſcending into hell?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> That he by humble ſuffering of tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ouercame hell.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> Is the wrath of Cod ſo fully conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and payed?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Yea. for God is welpleaſed in him.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> What was the cauſe of his riſing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine the third day?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> To iuſtifie vs.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> And doth it not aſſure vs of the great tryumph and victorie ouer ſinne, death, the diuell, and the power of hell?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Yea forſooth.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> Why did Chriſt after his riſing from death, goe to heauen?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> To prepare places for vs.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> Hath God the father handes?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> We may not ſo groſely imagine.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> Why then doeſt thou ſay that Chriſt ſitteth at the right hand? what doeſt thou confeſſe this hand to be?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> The power of God.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> So, then thou doeſt confeſſe that hée <pb facs="tcp:440:7"/> is God equall with the father.</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Truth it is.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> Shall not Chriſt come againe in the end of the world?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Yes, that I doe beléeue.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> What is the cauſe of his comming?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> To iudge the quicke and dead.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> What will he ſay to the faithfull in that day?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Come bleſſed of my father.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> What will hee ſay to them that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne his word and Sacraments?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Goe ye curſed.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> Whether doth he call the faithfull?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> To heauen.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> Whether doth he ſend the wicked?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> To hell.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> What is the holy Ghoſt?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> The third perſon in Trinitie.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> Why is he called holy?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Becauſe he maketh vs holy in the ſight of God.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> What is the Catholike Church?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Thoſe that beléeue in Chriſt of what nation ſoeuer they be.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> What are the ſaintes?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> The beléeuers.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:440:7"/>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> What is this Communion?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Communion is fellowſhip.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> Wherein haue the beléeuers a felow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippe?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> In the death of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> What ſignes and tokens he there of this fellowſhip in Chriſt his death?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Two ſignes and tokens.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> What be they onely called ſignes and tokens, are they not alſo named Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Yes, that is the more apt name.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> What is a Sacrament?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> A ſigne ſéene, declaring Gods grace which we can not ſée.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> Who ordayned theſe Sacraments?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Chriſt our Sauiour.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> VVhy did he ordaine them?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> To declare Gods good will vnto vs.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> God in his worde hath made many promiſes to his Church: how are theſe promiſes ſealed vnto vs?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> By the vſe of the Sacraments.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> VVhere muſt we lay vp this Iewell and treaſure offered in the Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Io ur harts.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> VVhich be the two Sacraments?</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:440:8"/> 
               <hi>A.</hi> Baptiſme and the Lords ſupper.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> VVhat is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſigne ſéene at Baptiſme?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> VVater.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> The vſe of water is to waſh, but in the Sacrament, the vſe of it is not to waſh, but to ſignify the grace of God by ſome ſpirituall waſhing. Tell me therefrre what this water ſignifyeth?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> The waſhing away of our ſinnes.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> How are our ſinnes waſhed away?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> By the ſprinkling of the bloud of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt once ſhedde for all.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> Muſt that ſigne of this ſprinkling or waſhing be often done?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> No, but once for all.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> What is the ſigne ſéene at the Lords ſupper?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Bread and wine.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> Which is the grace which it decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> The body and bloud of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> Séeing the Lord hath giuen but one ſigne in Baptiſme, why hath he giuen vs two in the ſupper?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> To declare that he féedeth not vs to the halfe meale but wholy.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> Then, by this he is both our meat
<pb facs="tcp:440:8"/> and drinke?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Euen ſo is he.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> You before did confeſſe that Chriſt went vp to heauen, there to remaine vntil the day of iudgement: how ſhould he then be our meate and drinke, is he carnall meat?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> No truly.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> How then is hee meate or nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment vnto vs?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> By his word he nouriſheth vs.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> how doe we receaue him to bee our meat?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> By faith to féede our ſoules.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> Who doth giue him vnto vs?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> God the Father.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> How did God the Father giue him?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> In ſacrifice on the croſſe for vs.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> VVhat are wee that God gaue his ſonne to be ſlaine in ſacrifice for vs?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> We are miſerable &amp; wretched ſinners.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> Should we therfore continue in ſinne, becauſe the ſacrifice is made for ſinne?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> God forbid.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> VVhat is then required of vs?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Faith and Repentance.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> Cannot faith be without repentance?</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:440:9"/> 
               <hi>A.</hi> No, if it be true faith.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> May repentance be without faith?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> True repentance can not be without fayth.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> VVhat was Iudas repentance?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Deſperation.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> VVhy was it deſperation?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Becauſe he hanged himſelfe &amp; ſought his owne death.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> Shall our bodies riſe againe to life af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they be dead and buried?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> I beléeue they ſhall riſe againe.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> How ſhall this our ſinnefull body riſe at the day of iudgement?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> VVithout corruption?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> Why is this clauſe of life euerlaſting, ſet to the end of the beléefe?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> To aſſure vs of immortalitie.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> What is meant by this word, Amen, in the end of the Créede?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> By it I deſire the increaſe of faith, &amp; the ſubuerſion of ſinne in me.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> How commeth the knowledge of ſin?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> By the law.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> What is the lawe?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Our ſchoolemaſter to driue vs to Chriſt.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:440:9"/>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> How did God deliuer this lawe vnto his ſeruant Moſes?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Written in two tables of ſtone.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> How many co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandements are there in the firſt table?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Foure Commandements.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> What doo theſe foure co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandements teach vs?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Our dutie towards God.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> How many Commandements are in the ſecond table?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Sixe Commandements.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> What doo theſe ſixe commandements teach vs?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Our dutie to our neighbour.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> VVhy is the dutie to God, ſet before the dutie to our neighbour?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Becauſe wee ſhould ſerue him aboue all things.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> And why art thou taught thy dutie to thy neighbour?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> That it might be knowen whether I doe my dutie to God, or no.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> How many Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts be there?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Ten.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> Which be they?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> God ſpake theſe wordes and ſayd.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:440:10"/>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> Is this a commandement?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> No. but a preface vnto them.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> What learneſt thou by theſe wordes then?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> I learne that God was the author of them.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> So, then I perceiue thou doeſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe it to be Gods word?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Yea that doe I.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> VVhat doeſt thou gather in thoſe wordes? I am the Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> By this word, Lord, I gather that he is of power to puniſh the offenders.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> What comfort haue wee in theſe? which brought thée out of the lande of Egypt, out of the houſe of bondage.</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> I gather this comfort, that God is the deliuerer of me and all the faithfull from hell, as he deliuered Iſrael from Egypt.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> What doeſt thou learne by this commandement? Thou ſhalt haue none other Gods but me.</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> I learne hereby to reioyce onely in the Lorde God, and to reſt in him one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> What ſhall we ſay of thoſe that truſt <pb facs="tcp:440:10"/> in Saintes and Angels, and make them as intereceſſors to God for them? doe they fulfill this commandement?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> They can not.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> How ſo?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Becauſe they reſt not onely in Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> In the ſecond commandement why doth God forbid the making of Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and the likeneſſe of any other thing?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Becauſe they diſhonour him.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> In that he forbiddeth vs to knéele be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them or to worſhip them: what would he haue vs to do?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> To worſhip the Lord God onely and ſerue him.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> How ſhould he be worſhipped?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> In ſpirite and in trueth.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> VVhy doth God call himſelfe a gea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous God viſiting the ſinnes of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> To ſhew his anger againſt Idolaters</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> What call you Idolaters?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Thoſe which maintaine ſuperſtitious doctrine.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> How doth the Lord promiſe to ſhewe
<pb facs="tcp:440:11"/> himſelfe to ſuch as loue him, and ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour themſelues to kéepe his comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> He will be mercifull to ſuch.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> What art thou commanded in the third commandement?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> I am commanded reuerently to vſe the name of God, in all my doings that I goe about.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> What are you forbidden to doe?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> All ſwearing, curſing and banning of any thing that he hath made.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> If a man or woman, whether it be, call God to record in a falſe matter: doth he vſe Gods name reuerently?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> No, but calleth him to be his conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nor.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> How is the Sabboth day kept holy?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> In hearing &amp; learning the holy word of God.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> It is apparant that in this fourth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement is expreſſed to kinds of la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, the one of the bodie, the other of the minde, the one earthly the other heauenly, are both theſe labours forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den in this commandement?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> No, but the one.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> VVhich is forbidden?</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:440:11"/> 
               <hi>A.</hi> The bodely labour.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> Then thou confeſſeſt that the ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all &amp; heauenly labour ought to be done: what ſhould wee ſéeke for in this hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly labour?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> The kingdom of heauen and the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> What ſhall we ſay of thoſe that will not come at the Church to learne the way to heauen and to vnderſtande the right pointes of Gods lawe?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Such regarde not Gods commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> In the fift co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement what mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth this word honor?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> To honour, is to obey, feare, relieue and ſerue.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> What meaneth this worde? father and mother.</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> By father and mother I vnderſtande all that haue any office or authoritie o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vs.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> As how for example?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> As the Prince ouer the people, the maieſtrates ouer the places where they rule, the miniſters ouer their charge or pariſh, the maiſters and dames ouer <pb facs="tcp:440:12"/> their ſeruants, fathers and mothers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer their children.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> Doeſt thou hereby acknowledge that thoſe that are ouer others, ſhould teach them that are vnder them?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> They ought to learne Gods word to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> end they might teach others y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> Ought not the ſubiects, towneſmen, ſeruants, and children to be diligent in learning of Gods word?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Yea, if not, they diſobey Gods com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandemet.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> VVhy is the promiſe of long life ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to this commandement?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> To encourage vs vnto the better per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of our dutie in obeying.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> In this ſixt commaundement, Thou ſhalt doe no murther, doth God onely forbid the outward act of murther, and not alſo the conſent vnto murther?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Yea, he forbiddeth the conſent vnto murther.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> Doth it forbid nothing elſe?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> It alſo forbiddeth vs anger &amp; malice.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> What doe thoſe that reuile, mocke &amp; deſpiſe others be they neuer ſo ſimple?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Such doe alſo againſt this comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:440:12"/>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> What ſay you of pride, ſurfetting and dronkennes, whether be they murther or not?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> They be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> greateſt kind of murther.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> How ſo?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Becauſe they hurt the ſoule and doe great diſhonor to God which made vs to ſet forth his glorie.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> In the vij. commandement, Thou ſhalt not commit adulterie, what doth the Lord require at our hands?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> To kéepe our bodies as fit veſſels for the holy Ghoſt to dwell in.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> Doth he only forbid the outward fact of whoredome and adulterie?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> He forbiddeth vs the very thought and enticement to ſuch lewdnes, as well as the outward fact.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> What meaneth this eight comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, Thou ſhalt not ſteale.</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> That I ſhould refraine from hurting any, by taking from them that which is theires.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> Doth this worde ſteale ſignify no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but taking away and robbing?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Yea: if I kéepe from another that
<pb facs="tcp:440:13"/> which he hath laboured for, I ſteale be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I giue him not his duetie.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> What are we commanded?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> To liue a contented life.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> What ſhal we ſay of thoſe that kéepe the knowledge of Gods worde from the ſimple and ignorant, which Chriſt would haue to be taught?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Such alſo ſteale, becauſe they doe withhold the truth. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 10. 10.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> What art thou taught by this ninth commandement, Thou ſhalt not beare falſe witneſſe againſt thy neighbour?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> I am taught to ſpeake nothing but truth, neither for the loue nor hatred of any.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> What doe you ſay of lyers, ſlaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, and ſuch as are buſie bodies, med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of ſuch thinges as they haue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to do withall.</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Such regarde not this law of God.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> What is this tenth commandement, Thou ſhalt not couet thy neighbours houſe, wife, goodes, ſeruant, nor any thing els which is his?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> It is a bridle vnto my minde.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> What learneſt thou to doe by it?</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:440:13"/> 
               <hi>A.</hi> To reſraine from wiſhing any thing at all to my neighbours hurt or hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, be it neuer ſo ſmall.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> VVhat is the ſhort ſumme and effect of the tenne Commandements?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> To loue God aboue all thinges, and my neighbour as my ſelfe..</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> Art thou able to kéepe theſe comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements of thy ſelfe?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Of my ſelfe I am not able to kéepe the leaſt of the tenne, if I could tell which it were.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> How ſhall we then ſatiſfie the lawe?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> By Chriſt, for he hath fulfilled it for vs.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> Should we liue careles becauſe Chriſt hath fulfilled the lawe?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> God forbid.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> VVhat muſt we doe then?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Learne to pray vnto the Lord God in the only name of his ſonne Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus our Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> How muſt it be then that we pray?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Thus, Our father which art in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> Why doeſt thou call God father?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Becauſe by faith in Chriſt we be cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen <pb facs="tcp:440:14"/> for the children of God. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 1. 12.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> Why ſayeſt thou our father, and not my father.</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Becauſe he is not only my father, but alſo the father of all the faithfull.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> Is God no where but in heauen?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Yes, he is in all places at once, and therefore in our Créede, we call him al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> VVhy doth our maiſter Chriſt teach vs to ſay heauen?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Becauſe in praying we ſhould lift vp our mindes to heauen whether hee is gone before.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> VVhat deſire you in this petition? Hallowed be thy name.</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Here we deſire God to giue vs grace that we may reuerently eſtéeme of his holy word which teacheth him vnto vs.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> What more doe we pray for?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> That we might liue a holy life agrée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to his word.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> VVhat doth Chriſt teach vs to pray for, in this petition? Thy kingdome come.</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> That the loue of God might be amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g vs, and that his worde which teacheth <pb facs="tcp:440:14"/> him vnto vs, might fréely of vs be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> How ſhould this bee knowen, that Gods loue is among vs?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> By this, if we haue loue one to an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> VVhat more are we taught?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> VVe are alſo taught to pray for a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient wayting for of his comming to iudgment.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> Are we not alſo in this petitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> taught to pray for the encreaſe of faith?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Yea, for the more that our faith en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeth, the more doth Gods kingdom encreaſe.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> In that Chriſt teacheth vs to pray that Gods will may be done, in earth as it is in heauen: what doth he ſéeme to forbid?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> In teaching vs ſo to pray, hee woulde not haue vs to ſéeke our owne wils, or to ſticke to our owne wiſedom.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> Then it foloweth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we pray againſt pride, couetouſnes, extortion, vſury, bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery, exceſſe, dronkennes; whoredome, theft, lying &amp; ſuch like vices, for theſe be the will of man, &amp; contrarie to the will <pb facs="tcp:440:15"/> of God.</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> VVe doe ſo I confeſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> If we pray againſt thoſe ſinners, and to be endewed with righteouſneſſe, and yet take a delight in them: what doe we?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Euen mocke with God, and ſo doe heape puniſhment vpon our ſelues for it.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> Becauſe I ſée this to be againſt mee, ſhould I not therefore pray?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> If we ſhould not pray, we were the deſpiſers of his commandement. <hi>Mark.</hi> 14. 38.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> VVhat are we here taught to aſke? giue vs this day our daily bread.</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> All thinges neceſſarie to this preſent life.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> Why doth he teach vs to pray day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for dayly bread?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Becauſe without his dayly bleſſing our food could giue ſmall nouriſhment vnto vs.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> What deſire ye in this petition: For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue vs our treſpaſſes.</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Here I deſire his mercy: for vnleſſe he be pitifull vnto vs, we are readie to <pb facs="tcp:440:15"/> fall into vtter deſtruction.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> What meaneth the condition? As we forgiue them that treſpaſſe againſt vs.</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Here we deſire, that it may bee his pleaſure to giue vs grace that we may be ready to pardon thoſe that haue of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended vs.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> Why doe you ſay? Leade vs not into temptation?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Here we pray that God will not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer vs to be ouercome of temptation: but that being for our profit or tryall, we might boldly bee ſtrengthened in him to abide that which his pleaſure is to lay vpon vs.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> Why is this added? For thine is the kingdome, the power and the glory for euer.</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> This doth teach vs to confeſſe that all rule and authoritie doth come from God, and ruleth all thinges according to his will.</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> VVhy ſayeſt thou, Amen, in the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter end of the prayer?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> By that word I deſire the Lord God to graunt all thinges which before I <pb facs="tcp:440:16"/> prayed for.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> Tell me the effect in few wordes of all that thou haſt ſaide vpon the Lordes Prayer?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> I deſire Gods grace to doe his will, and thinges neceſſarie both to body and ſoule.</p>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer.</head>
               <p>THe Lord giue vs grace to lay theſe thinges vp déepely in our harts, and alwaies to be mindfull of them, as it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hooueth his true and faithfull Children in Chriſt Ieſus. So be it.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:440:16"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
